<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><rss xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom' xmlns:openSearch='http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearchrss/1.0/' xmlns:georss='http://www.georss.org/georss' xmlns:thr='http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0' version='2.0'><channel><atom:id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754</atom:id><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 17:49:59 +0000</lastBuildDate><title>Dégage la voie</title><description></description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/</link><managingEditor>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</managingEditor><generator>Blogger</generator><openSearch:totalResults>39</openSearch:totalResults><openSearch:startIndex>1</openSearch:startIndex><openSearch:itemsPerPage>25</openSearch:itemsPerPage><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-7583066344690571790</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 17:49:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-03-23T10:49:59.732-07:00</atom:updated><title>A small celebration at least</title><description>Since I've had a lot of setbacks lately, I have to celebrate one nice milestone. I created my first component offset in Sketchup. What does that mean?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-z2ybnK-QQXo/TYoxDvFYS-I/AAAAAAAAAM0/U9kv8KkwuxE/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.42.21+PM.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="312" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-z2ybnK-QQXo/TYoxDvFYS-I/AAAAAAAAAM0/U9kv8KkwuxE/s400/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.42.21+PM.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;First it means that my offset selection tool works well enough that I can select two arbitrary points on the streets and form a path between them. The tool allows me to select what side of the street I want, or I can select the center. Then I can decide where I want to lay my tracks:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-0ACt5udZKS4/TYoxoEWULiI/AAAAAAAAAM4/evnMMmdeal4/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.44.17+PM.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="254" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-0ACt5udZKS4/TYoxoEWULiI/AAAAAAAAAM4/evnMMmdeal4/s320/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.44.17+PM.png" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When I'm satisfied I click to finalize the path &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-mUT22KpOqUY/TYovF_HvXrI/AAAAAAAAAMs/dpOImwe2sdQ/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.32.06+PM.png" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="515" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-mUT22KpOqUY/TYovF_HvXrI/AAAAAAAAAMs/dpOImwe2sdQ/s640/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.32.06+PM.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-jtesK1MohNg/TYovmLQWdYI/AAAAAAAAAMw/uxhOQIm9cDA/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.32.32+PM.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="257" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-jtesK1MohNg/TYovmLQWdYI/AAAAAAAAAMw/uxhOQIm9cDA/s320/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.32.32+PM.png" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&amp;nbsp;Whether tracks, bike lanes, road markings, or a dinosaur trail, I can now enable users to put anything down along the path they desire. Tracks are super easy because all you have to do is define the cross section of the rail and then have it follow a line to create the 3D rail. But more complicated types of paths aren't that much harder. I could make railroad ties that follow the line as well, as long I defined how I wanted them spaced.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some future steps will be to curve the line so there are no awkward angles for the rail as seen in the intersection above. But first I'll probably define a few more components, like a bike lane (and dinosaur trail) to test out the new technology.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Personally, my biggest waste of time when doing site designs was trying to draw offsets well, whether I was making sidewalks, tracks, or lane markings. Making this tool work well will be the biggest benefit to me in my future use of Sketchup for site design.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-mUT22KpOqUY/TYovF_HvXrI/AAAAAAAAAMs/dpOImwe2sdQ/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.32.06+PM.png" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-7583066344690571790?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/03/small-celebration-at-least.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-z2ybnK-QQXo/TYoxDvFYS-I/AAAAAAAAAM0/U9kv8KkwuxE/s72-c/Screen+shot+2011-03-23+at+1.42.21+PM.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-6999387731632700978</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2011 14:36:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-03-23T07:47:51.037-07:00</atom:updated><title>Transit Car Comparison</title><description>Until I figure out a good way to convert my work in drawing programs (I use OmniGraffle) to a web format, I'm forced to link to a PDF. Please click the image to read this post.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/uc?id=0B_ozQMe1Y1P8NjllZWI3OTktY2IwOS00MjM5LWFkY2MtZmQ5MTM4NTFkMzEw&amp;amp;export=download&amp;amp;hl=en" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="320" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Pe4thM8_2ZY/TYoHulhkwUI/AAAAAAAAAMo/QijsqdOL1h8/s320/Transit+Car+Comparison.png" width="102" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-6999387731632700978?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/03/transit-car-comparison.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-Pe4thM8_2ZY/TYoHulhkwUI/AAAAAAAAAMo/QijsqdOL1h8/s72-c/Transit+Car+Comparison.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-3806394759600065021</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 14:06:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-03-14T07:06:53.962-07:00</atom:updated><title>Who's transit system?</title><description>In &lt;i&gt;A Pattern Language&lt;/i&gt; by Christopher Alexander, he makes the case for neighborhoods contracting their own transit provider to connect them with a network of other places. The well-intentioned premise is that neighborhoods know best how to serve themselves, and that a mandated system aways leads to the common service problems that we see today (I'm recalling this from memory since my checked out library book was just recalled!)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;With that in mind, yesterday I tried to go to a beach with a friend in Boston. I didn't really care what beach it was, though a little nature would have been better than a city beach. I checked my options on the North and South Shore using Google Maps and found that the commuter trains running each way weren't frequent enough to make a few hours at the beach possible. I also found that I had no access to a car that day. Therefore I settled on Revere Beach, which is right on the Blue Line subway. It would take about a 50 minutes to get there from my local subway stop, fine:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="350" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" scrolling="no" src="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&amp;amp;source=s_d&amp;amp;saddr=Davis+Square,+Somerville,+MA&amp;amp;daddr=Revere+Beach+Station&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=Fd3mhgIddcHC-ylXXAToGHfjiTFStVsdfwKRow%3BFaIXhwIda73E-ym_lAIyBW7jiTH9jVn-Fa6bPg&amp;amp;mra=ltm&amp;amp;dirflg=r&amp;amp;ttype=dep&amp;amp;date=03%2F14%2F11&amp;amp;time=9:02am&amp;amp;noexp=0&amp;amp;noal=0&amp;amp;sort=def&amp;amp;sll=42.402418,-71.057854&amp;amp;sspn=0.124731,0.187111&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=42.40039,-71.057854&amp;amp;spn=0.05218,0.13075&amp;amp;start=0&amp;amp;output=embed" width="425"&gt;&amp;amp;lt;p&amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br&amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;fsdfsd&amp;amp;lt;/p&amp;amp;gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The equivalent car ride is 23 minutes, though I would have gone to a nicer beach with a car. Also, the subway ride would be shorter if the Blue Line connected directly to the Red Line, which is something that has been planned and should have happened a long time ago. We road down to the point of the Blue Line transfer at Government Center, at which point the driver informed us that the Blue Line was closed for maintenance and that buses would serve the route. I had run into this problem a couple weeks ago on the weekend, and it turns out that they have been renovating station platforms at two stops on the weekends. But the announcement made it sound like the entire line was closed, not just two stations (I found no evidence of the former online.) Thus my quick decision was to remain on the Green Line up to North Station and simply walk to Revere Beach via Charlestown. Well, anyone who knows the area would chuckle at my folly. The walk is several miles and the Tobin Bridge is not accessible to pedestrians, meaning a costly detour of several more miles. We ended up riding a delayed bus back to downtown and gave up on the beach.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder="0" height="350" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" scrolling="no" src="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&amp;amp;source=s_d&amp;amp;saddr=Davis+Square,+Somerville,+MA&amp;amp;daddr=Government+Center+Station,+Boston,+Suffolk,+Massachusetts+02109+to:USS+Constitution,+Boston,+MA+to:Monument+Square+to:Government+Center+Station,+Boston,+Suffolk,+Massachusetts+02109&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=Fd3mhgIddcHC-ylXXAToGHfjiTFStVsdfwKRow%3BFZlbhgId8bjD-ykTZFwChXDjiTHsbfZh-GOyrQ%3BFZCNhgIdnsLD-yFWrsiVPupa0g%3BFb6fhgIdCLHD-w%3BFZlbhgId8bjD-ykTZFwChXDjiTHsbfZh-GOyrQ&amp;amp;mra=dme&amp;amp;mrsp=3&amp;amp;sz=13&amp;amp;dirflg=w&amp;amp;sll=42.377441,-71.089611&amp;amp;sspn=0.06239,0.093555&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=42.377441,-71.089611&amp;amp;spn=0.06239,0.093555&amp;amp;output=embed" width="425"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Failed transit experiences are not uncommon to me, but this one was especially painful. I really wanted to go to a nice beach where I could escape the city, but it happened that I failed to even make it to a lousy city beach.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Getting back to &lt;i&gt;A Pattern Language&lt;/i&gt;, I think that Alexander is wrong to advocate contracted transit service. Such service ties you to a bus or shuttle and eliminates the possibility of rail, unless you somehow set up tracks and let competitors share them. That may work on an inter-city network, but it's probably impossible to implement within a region. However, I like the idea of neighborhoods taking control of their transit, rather than the city, region, or state making political decisions about how and how much to serve them. In a compact place like the Boston metro area, it's fairly easy to identify neighborhoods by their centers. I live in west Somerville but my local neighborhood center is Ball Square. The people who live near me might say that Powderhouse Square or Magoun Square are their centers, even though the former lacks retail and both lack good transit. In a compact place the neighborhood center must be less than a ten minute walk away. In a modern sprawl suburb I would be okay with fifteen minutes. It would be wise to identify the members of a neighborhood center and have representatives figure out how to serve them with transit. These representatives would meet with other representatives along each transit corridor that concerned them to find solutions. A city or regional facilitator would assist the group. Representatives would only be concerned about the corridor up to the point that it got them to a well-functioning subway or train station. (If that station wasn't functioning adequately, a higher scope group would have to address it.) In most cases the representatives would need work out improvements to a corridor to increase the level of service. They would identify the ideal service and then use software tools or an expert to determine its cost and funding options. It might turn out that the ideal service required a $100 million dollar investment to build a modern streetcar to a subway station what was two miles away from the end of the corridor (The Grand/Lakeshore to downtown Oakland neighborhoods in Oakland, CA are a perfect example of this.) The representatives would learn the per capita cost for capital and maintenance of the new line, given the total number of adults in the neighborhoods. It might be possible to subtract from this federal and state grants, as well as the operation costs saved by eliminating the existing inadequate service. The software or expert would also estimate the per capita benefits, quantifying savings in car use, pollution reduction, freed up space (from parking lot and car reduction), appreciated real estate, etc. Then the group would initiate legislation that created assessment fees on the residents and businesses to fund the system. The legislation would require a vote from only those in the neighborhoods and express in concrete language the exact service, costs, and estimated benefits. Of course, no such voting process exists where neighborhoods one or more cities can exclusively vote for something.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This fantasy of mine is unrealistic because we have such weak neighborhood cohesiveness. But the current method of top-down transit decisions is clearly failing in a political environment where public spending is demonized and taxes are abhorred. There's no easy top-down fix to my problem of getting to a beach in a reasonable amount of time on transit. It requires that each neighborhood care about their transit system and that the regional service be taken seriously by all levels of government. If I lived in Europe it would easy, but they don't seem to mind sending trains everywhere at great cost &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; benefit to their people.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-3806394759600065021?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/03/whos-transit-system.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-116562296586266721</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2011 15:58:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-03-10T06:15:39.690-08:00</atom:updated><title>Bus Rapid Transit from an expert</title><description>In a class yesterday evening I was fortunate to listen to a presentation by Paul Schimek, a senior transportation planner            &lt;span class="at"&gt;at &lt;/span&gt;       TranSystems and a BRT expert. I've written quite a bit on this blog about my &lt;a href="http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/search?q=brt"&gt;misgivings&lt;/a&gt; about BRT, so I was eager to hear from a strong advocate and ask him some questions. The centerpiece of Paul's presentation was the BRT system, TransMilenio in Bogotá, which set the modern standard for BRT by the foundations of a comprehensive system.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-v4b6dhG2qDQ/TXeCcn4J31I/AAAAAAAAAL0/ggt_3s4wgJQ/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-09+at+8.34.38+AM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="314" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-v4b6dhG2qDQ/TXeCcn4J31I/AAAAAAAAAL0/ggt_3s4wgJQ/s640/Screen+shot+2011-03-09+at+8.34.38+AM.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-vd_ibrmWFb4/TXeCRzv4BFI/AAAAAAAAALw/_pWfcE53QnM/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-07+at+5.40.31+PM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;http://www.transmilenio.gov.co/pdf/MiPlanDeViaje.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LxCuPLz5Y9w/TXeDv4P0cpI/AAAAAAAAAL4/roLp3ZTQp2M/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-09+at+8.41.58+AM.png" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="155" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LxCuPLz5Y9w/TXeDv4P0cpI/AAAAAAAAAL4/roLp3ZTQp2M/s320/Screen+shot+2011-03-09+at+8.41.58+AM.png" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It's an impressive system that was built to strict BRT standards--dedicated lanes, or &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=0CBoQFjAA&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.nbrti.org%2Fdocs%2Fpdf%2FBRT%2520Network%2520Planning%2520Study%2520-%2520Final%2520Report.pdf&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=brt%20network%20planning%20study&amp;amp;ei=QoN3Tcb1JZOJ0QHZzZDnBg&amp;amp;usg=AFQjCNGM_L1pQCt98mZwiYcx3hlXA56wWQ&amp;amp;sig2=HeYiGgaFnvP7NhWNBLzUmQ&amp;amp;cad=rja"&gt;quickways&lt;/a&gt;, prepaid boardings, platforms level with the bus to avoid steps, ultra-modern articulated buses, etc. What's more, a second part of the system not shown on the map above is an entire network of feeder buses to the trunk lines. Many of the quickways are double lanes in both directions to allow for passing, which is required to accommodate local and limited service. BRT was used in place of rail for the reduced time and cost of development. The cost for the initial segment was US$5.9 million/km, has 1.4 million riders a day in 2009, enjoyed 75% approval (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TransMilenio#Costs.2C_ridership.2C_and_impact"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.) The system opened in 2000 after only a couple years of development, according to Paul. There are a score of other noteworthy topics about TransMilenio, including the financing and contracting with pre-existing private operators.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Paul also described the BRT project in Ottawa, which is an older system constructed along unused highway lanes that had been intended for highway expansion. I had a couple questions about BRT that I was able to inject at this point. I road the Ottawa buses in January from the Via Rail train station just outside downtown to the city center. My experience was poor. We exited the train station at around 9pm on a weeknight. I had been tracking the required bus on my iphone and it was also listed on a monitor in the train station. The connection would be tight, and unfortunately it required us to cross the wide street in front of the station and proceed through a covered corridor (think airport parking lot connection). At the end of the corridor we followed stairs leading down to the busway, which in this case was a lane down below the main street. As we negotiated the last flight of stairs with our large backpacks I saw a bus pull up and take off. We walked down to the bus shelter dispirited. There was no digital sign to indicate the next bus, but I knew they were twenty minutes apart. You can imagine that the temperature was around 0˚F, and the shelter was no more than cold metal enclosure. So we trudged back up the stairs, back across the walkway and street, and plopped down in the train station to await the next bus. Upon boarding the next bus we were took a series of quickways and shared roads. The buses were nothing special, the stops were ugly and minimal, as you would expect along a highway. We alighted at a nondescript intersection that was near our lodging. The bus was in local mode at that point, since one could get off every few blocks. The Ottawa train station serves direct connections from Toronto and Montreal, thus it is well used. I can't imagine why you would want visitors and businesspeople to arrive at the gateway to the nation's capital and jump on a bus. In fact, there are plans to replace this route with light rail.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To be fair, the Ottawa system lacks some BRT characteristics, such as pre-pay, level-boarding, modern buses, and upgrading stops to "stations." After disparaging the system in front of the class, I next asked Paul about the qualitative differences between BRT and light-rail/streetcars. Ottawa is not a pretty city, and the bus system seems to match the look of the city, even right in front of the beautiful national parliament building and Fairmont Hotel. I referenced the beautiful city centers in Europe that make use of light-rail/streetcar service in largely pedestrianized areas. Is there not a symbiotic relationship between a city's surface transit system and the city itself? In other words, a beautiful center in Europe theses days often begets a beautiful transit system, because anything less would not be fitting with the desired feel of the place. But it seems like there is also some knack for a beautiful transit system to spread beauty to its surroundings. Glancing at some Portland, OR streetcar images, there certainly seems to be some beautification that accompanies it:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.dogcaught.com/rfimg/0605/streetcar-psu.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="167" src="http://www.dogcaught.com/rfimg/0605/streetcar-psu.jpg" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2BwtdzAJ-N4/SOHueVXiYyI/AAAAAAAAF3k/kRTVXmwv1Bw/s400/DSCN2329_2069.JPG" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="150" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2BwtdzAJ-N4/SOHueVXiYyI/AAAAAAAAF3k/kRTVXmwv1Bw/s200/DSCN2329_2069.JPG" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Of course, these landscape improvements are often coupled with streetcar projects and cost money. But I think the idea of "coupling" is the key here. When you tear up the street to put in streetcar tracks, you might as well tear up the area around and make it look nice, even if it's just the station area. Check out the light rail station in downtown Calgary:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.lightrail.com/photos/calgary/calgary05.jpg" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="http://www.lightrail.com/photos/calgary/calgary05.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ugh, why didn't they take the asphalt out? This is a pedestrianized street! Calgary's system is a few decades old now, and I don't think planners would make this mistake nowadays with downtown rail. When you couple landscape improvements with rail installation, you achieve an implicit or explicit cascading effect to the surroundings. The street is nicer &lt;i&gt;and &lt;/i&gt;has good access, so it attracts the type of people that want unique shops, nice housing, etc. It doesn't mean that the surrounding buildings must be leveled and rebuilt to &lt;a href="http://www.ifc.com/portlandia/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Portlandia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; standards, but there is pedestrian-oriented, intellectual transformation of the place.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Can BRT achieve the coupling effect? Yes and no. One reason we install BRT is to save money. This often means that there is no additional money available for streetscape improvements. That's not a failing of BRT, but it's just a common precursor to BRT projects. To not spend the extra money on coupled streetscape improvements is foolish--half the point of new rail or BRT is to aesthetically distinguish it from the previous modes to enhance attraction to the service and surroundings (the other half being the improved level of service characteristics.) There have clearly been landscape improvements associated with the Transmilenio project, so I won't write off BRT's ability to couple:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://imgpe.trivago.com/uploadimages/49/35/493566_l.jpeg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="http://imgpe.trivago.com/uploadimages/49/35/493566_l.jpeg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;I fear that in the US political context, as Paul testified, BRT will mostly be the solution for projects that fail to receive federal funding for rail. This lead to my other concern about BRT, which is that its &lt;b&gt;mode equivalency &lt;/b&gt;with traditional bus service makes it an easy target for corner cutting. One may decide to build BRT, but if it's possible to save money by not having all dedicated lanes, not have special vehicles, not repaving the street to give the feeling of a fixed guideway, etc., then oftentimes those features will be cut from the project. And this seems to be common in the US. Boston's Silver Line cut corners at every turn. The Washington St. line has next-to-no dedicated lanes, and both lines rumble over the same bumpy streets as any other buses. They mostly lack prepaid boarding, have no step-free platforms, and lack a score of other fundamental BRT features. With streetcars and light rail, there is no mode equivalency, except when cities unwisely put streetcars on shared lanes with car traffic. Because surface rail requires a major change to the street service and requires a different type of rolling stock, compromises are hard to make. Plus, the higher cost of installation and vehicle acquisition make some compromises nonsensical. If you are going to put rail on a shared car lane, you might as well leave it as a bus. If you are going to regularly run buses over your dedicated streetcar lanes &lt;i&gt;in place &lt;/i&gt;of the streetcars themselves, you might as well have left it as a bus (i.e. it's only financial sound to replace streetcars with buses for occasional maintenance or emergencies, and it's okay to let buses share the streetcar lane but not replace them.) It turns out the most common failing of surface rail projects is putting in too many stops and not giving signal priority.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Paul also argues effectively that BRT can be not just equivalent to rail but better, because it gives you more direct link capability (BRT buses can go off the dedicated lanes onto shared streets, whereas rail riders must alight and jump on a local bus.) I agree that not transferring is nice, but it's possible to have a trunk light-rail line that is easy to access without requiring local bus connectors. Europe succeeds at this remarkably well with friendly biking streets. In fact, having only trunk lines or no transfer-free service may even encourage better decisions about the character of a neighborhood. Taking people the first or last mile using buses without a transfer may encourage us to leave the local streets as they are--car dominated and unlivable. When you create a trunk network and put radii around each station to see whom it serves, it can lead to a good discussion about friendly networks to access the station, whether on foot, bike, personal electric motorized transport, or bus. Here's a radius map I made for a BART station in El Cerrito, CA:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://362600631155269084-a-likuski-org-s-sites.googlegroups.com/a/likuski.org/urbanism/Home/small-project-series/Image%2012.png?attachauth=ANoY7cpzAetXhNT29NDThE28XP7EHYuE5LZwsgXhz7PhIPAc5wEMs_-q4mik0KgvESQ0gB-xvFWa4RjQFyNh-0GrSOG4Aj6gtSSUvEszIZo6R0mndAUL0iMpcxt36q9jzj7RqRsquJCl6U5HW-k9VO0eNlR6XcvzY9-2s_wjHVYVWDOTL8188Xk3JNRSPlxFaG-CJJBLLXpeVliaCECYQ8N1R_r6CESyMSo85awSnvUqmzpPITD-Yck%3D&amp;amp;attredirects=0" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="320" src="https://362600631155269084-a-likuski-org-s-sites.googlegroups.com/a/likuski.org/urbanism/Home/small-project-series/Image%2012.png?attachauth=ANoY7cpzAetXhNT29NDThE28XP7EHYuE5LZwsgXhz7PhIPAc5wEMs_-q4mik0KgvESQ0gB-xvFWa4RjQFyNh-0GrSOG4Aj6gtSSUvEszIZo6R0mndAUL0iMpcxt36q9jzj7RqRsquJCl6U5HW-k9VO0eNlR6XcvzY9-2s_wjHVYVWDOTL8188Xk3JNRSPlxFaG-CJJBLLXpeVliaCECYQ8N1R_r6CESyMSo85awSnvUqmzpPITD-Yck%3D&amp;amp;attredirects=0" width="311" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Here I pointed out that the outer 2 mile radius could be covered in just 12 minutes by an electric bike on a steep hill, and just as fast by a regular bike in the non-hilly parts. The local buses are useful, but they happen to fit in with the car-heavy status quo.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I think the real problem with the bus transfer to rail is that the buses are typically not synced to the predictable rail lines. Countless times I've alighted the train only to see the bus depart oblivious of the train schedule. If you make sure the local buses have carfree lanes, signal priority, and sync with the train schedule, you solve most of the problem with transfers. Oh, and no double fares or transfer fees, of course! Or better yet, make your local buses free.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, I believe there is a real qualitative difference between modern rail and modern BRT buses. Rail is smooth, easier to automate to reduce jerks (noticeable changes in acceleration), it's safer, and there is something magical about rail that is hard to capture in even the most perfect BRT bus, even an electric, battery powered bus. As a country built on inter- and inner-urban rail that we lost to the bizarre forces of history, I think we are entitled to want it back in modern form. The fact that we chronically under-finance transit while cars bathe in hidden subsidies and dreadful externalities means that we have the capability to shift the money and space wasted on cars to high quality transit systems.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Paul made me think highly of BRT, and it's certainly a friend in the battle against car-dominated cities. From a people-moving perspective BRT matches up well and even exceeds rail in some ways. But movement is part of the larger ecosystem, and when you look beyond movement rail looks stronger. The 1) lack of mode equivalence of rail that reduces corner-cutting, 2) its somewhat stronger ability to be a place-maker (however unfair to BRT), 3) its tangible comforts and intangible qualities, and 4) its history as the post-industrial shaper of the nation and cities still make it the best surface transit choice whenever possible. Others have made similar conclusions, but I needed to reaffirm my intuitions by mulling this over.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span id="goog_905916421"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span id="goog_905916422"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-LxCuPLz5Y9w/TXeDv4P0cpI/AAAAAAAAAL4/roLp3ZTQp2M/s1600/Screen+shot+2011-03-09+at+8.41.58+AM.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-116562296586266721?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/03/bus-rapid-transit-from-expert.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2BwtdzAJ-N4/SOHueVXiYyI/AAAAAAAAF3k/kRTVXmwv1Bw/s72-c/DSCN2329_2069.JPG' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-8834264989661554877</guid><pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2011 15:09:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-03-06T10:29:56.436-08:00</atom:updated><title>What if a street decided to go car-free?</title><description>Dear Mayor,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On behalf of the residents of &lt;i&gt;X &lt;/i&gt;Avenue, I hereby formally request we be allowed to permitted to pedestrianize our street to restore the street for use by the community rather than cars. We specifically wish to limit the use of our street to pedestrians, cyclists, emergency vehicles, motorized access for disabled persons, and deliveries. We wish to eliminate all other private auto traffic and ban any parking on the street. Though some of us will initially maintain vehicles on our private property for occasional use, our long-term goal is to eliminate vehicle ownership and prohibit it using a special zoning designation. Residents of the street will transition to use of car-share programs or no car at all. We request that the city make a minor financial contribution to this important step in improving our neighborhood. Specifically we desire that the city install official signs designating the street to be pedestrianized and install obstructions that discourage casual vehicle use (the details of which may be discussed later.) We also request that the city contribute equipment to remove the asphalt from the street. We will replace the asphalt with attractive paving elements and greenery at our own expense. This signals our commitment to improving and maintaining our street as neighbors, which we think is the correct model for all neighborhood streets. We will naturally conform with safety and accessibility standards, and we will proceed only once our plans are approved. This may also be an appropriate opportunity for the city to bury our utility lines, for which we will share in the expense.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The goal of this innovative project is to strengthen our neighborhood and community by creating a safe and beautiful public space in which children and adults may loiter without fear of automobiles. Other benefits include removal of impervious surface, new trees, and a subsequent increase in our properties values, which will directly benefit the city via property taxes. Our broader goal is to create the beginning of a new network of carfree streets that are desirable to pedestrians, cyclists, and resdents. In conjunction with our efforts, we expect the city to invest substantially in transit improvements--especially streetcar service along our busiest streets. Toward this goal we will gladly pay assessment fees that reflect the value added to our neighborhood by the new transit service.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We look forward to hearing from your office about our plan at your earliest convenience. Please contact our neighborhood liaison &lt;i&gt;X &lt;/i&gt;listed below. She will follow up with a visit to you office in two weeks time if she has not hear back from you.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sincerely, the property owners of &lt;i&gt;X &lt;/i&gt;Avenue&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dorothy Smith, Neighborhood Liason, owner 22 &lt;i&gt;X &lt;/i&gt;Avenue&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;555-555-5555&lt;br /&gt;dorothy@smith.fam&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ken and Maria Buckles, owners 41 &lt;i&gt;X &lt;/i&gt;Avenue&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sally Worthm owner of 29 &lt;i&gt;X &lt;/i&gt;Avenue&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;...&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-8834264989661554877?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/03/what-if-street-decided-to-go-car-free.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-1183767161252747275</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2011 17:16:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-02-21T09:16:56.399-08:00</atom:updated><title>The lack of high-profile local transit advocacy groups</title><description>When considering advocacy power, one needs to consider two dimensions about its advocates--whether their geographic (or perhaps socio-economic) situation is dispersed versus concentrated and whether the issue of interest has a narrow or broad scope. For transit systems, the users tend to be dispersed geographically, unless the transit system is limited to one line of service. The importance of the transit system has fairly narrow focus for most transit users, because they rely on it to get to and from work in a timely matter, but it is broad in that people have different ideas about what it lacks. The most powerful advocates tend to be concentrated with narrow focus.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The MBTA in Boston is used by a broad group of users of every socio-economic background. The decline of transit over much of the 20th century has left MBTA riders with little in expectations of the system, even though it is essential to the metro area. Because of the low expectations and a geographically and socio-economically dispersed clientele, there is no strong advocacy group for the MBTA. The only group that I'm aware of is the &lt;a href="http://www.ace-ej.org/tru"&gt;T Riders Union&lt;/a&gt;, which tends to concente on the social justice problems, like cleaning up the bus fleets that are stored in poor neighborhoods. Boston should have a higher profile MBTA advocacy group, especially considering the highly educated population and business interests that rely on the transit network. Where is that group? Can advocates only rally around a certain transit project, like a line extension to their neighborhood? I'm happy to support any increase to MBTA funding that would result in expansion of the rail system. And I'm sure tens of thousands of people would join a group that lobbied for a better-funded MBTA. &lt;a href="http://www.thebostonchannel.com/news/18891367/detail.html"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the best link you can find on MBTA advocacy, the result of the good work of the T Riders Union, MASSPIRG, and the umbrella On The Move coalition. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It seems like we need a group narrowly focused on funding the MBTA to upgrade and expand the rail rapid transit and regional rail. This means serving current riders, from rich to poor, by upgrading bus lines to modern streetcars/light rail with dedicated lanes and signal priority, converting the commuter system into a regional system (frequent and electified service), and fighting to extract money from driving and parking to put into the system. Now, how can I get that started?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Calling on advocates for:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Modernization and expansion of the MBTA rail network.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Upgrade of many bus lines to streetcar/light rail on dedicated right-of-way with signal priority.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rejection of BRT (bus rapid transit) and fake BRT (i.e. MBTA's Silver Line) in favor of rail transit.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Institution of major new funding sources for the MBTA to be extracted from driving and parking to simultaneously encourage transit use and discourage driving.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;That seems pretty narrow in scope and highly desirable for many people.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-1183767161252747275?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/02/lack-of-high-profile-local-transit.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-4926575623766441846</guid><pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2011 16:30:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-03-13T08:01:37.236-07:00</atom:updated><title>Concerning the Boston Complete Streets Guide</title><description>I sent this email to bostoncompletestreets.org. I'm hopeful that they will respond.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Greetings,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was delighted to here Vineet Gupta's presentation to  Livable Streets last week, but I was rather dismayed to look over the &lt;a href="http://www.bostoncompletestreets.org/"&gt;Complete Streets  Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; and read nothing about rail-based transit, nor hear much  mention of it from Mr. Gupta. Although Boston has one of the more  comprehensive rail systems in the nation, there is clearly a need to  expand the system within and outside of the city. It is difficult to be  "complete" without considering subway and above-ground rail stations,  which are the ultimate place-makers in Boston and most other major  cities. I am well aware of the financing problems concerning rail  expansion, specifically the glaring problem that Boston cities are  directly responsible for funding their own streets but not their rail.  I'm also well aware that the there is no state bonding capacity left to  fund new projects. This means that the city must step up and fund its  own rail improvements, essentially through charging more for driving and  parking. We are already starting to see the consequences of neglecting  rail, as demonstrated in the projects like &lt;a href="http://www.somervillema.gov/spotlight.cfm?id=68"&gt;East Broadway in  Somerville&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.town.arlington.ma.us/public_documents/ArlingtonMA_Planning/MassAve/MassAvePresentation_042809.pdf"&gt;Mass  Ave in Arlington&lt;/a&gt;, where lane reductions would preclude the ability  to install (restore in fact) quality modern streetcar service on two  transit-starved corridors. Please update the guidelines to reflect how  existing and new rail is fundamental to complete streets. I would  appreciate hearing from someone about this important issue, especially  is there is any rational for omitting rail service from the guide.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Thank you,&lt;br /&gt;Andy Likuski&lt;br /&gt;Graduate Student of Tufts Department of Urban and Environmental Policy  and Planning&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-4926575623766441846?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/02/concerning-boston-complete-streets.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>1</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-6747280989744093889</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-02-09T10:52:47.541-08:00</atom:updated><title>The restaurant smoking analogy</title><description>I my unceasing attempts to appear thoughtful, I started scrambling for an analogy of trying to calm cars on city streets. The easiest analogy to materialize was that of indoor smoking, since indoor smoking has so recently been reduced from omnipresent to non-existent. I will present the stages of elimination of smoking in restaurants with the present and future steps to eliminate cars in cities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;In the beginning...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Smoking in restaurants was something that a lot of people did. Those that didn't just had to deal:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Lots of people drove cars in cities on every street according to traffic laws designed for cars. Those that didn't drive were marginalized. Everyone was endangered and old urban spaces were ruined while new ones were built wrong from the start.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;The minority, or majority in some places, started making a stink...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Non-smokers and concerned health policy-makers questioned the wisdom of exposing non-smokers to cigarette smoke in a confined place while they were trying to taste food.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pedestrians and concerned urban policy-makers exposed the disadvantages of building urban spaces for cars, especially the danger to pedestrians and destruction of communities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Token gestures were made...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Restaurants separated their tables into smoking and non-smoking sections. Smokers still got to smoke without restriction and non-smokers were still exposed to smoke in a confined place while trying to eat, put at least restaurants could make a show of concern.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Traffic engineers began making token gestures to pedestrians by emphasizing crosswalks, pushing out curbs, and retiming traffic signals. Drivers continued driving the same, the danger levels remained unacceptably high, and communities remained in ruins, but traffic engineers could claim concern for someone other than drivers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[This is the present reality of car calming in North America and in many countries]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Stronger, but inadequate measures were taken...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Restaurants installed strong ventilator systems over the smoking areas and sometimes even separated it into a separate room. Some of the health dangers to non-smokers were eliminated, but problems with low smoke levels remained as did the stench of stray third-hand smoke odor while people tried to eat. Restaurant workers continued to inhale all of the smoke.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Transportation engineers, city planners, and landscape architects began to calm streets of cars by radically altering the form of the street. They narrowed streets, resurfaced, removed traffic signs, and made key streets carfree. Light car use remained in "pedestrian areas" of the city while heavy traffic continued to circulate on major boulevards and other arterials as before.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;[This is the present car calming reality of many European urban spaces and some other places]&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;The offending activity was found to be completely incompatible and was eliminated...&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Many countries or states of countries have banned smoking completely in restaurants. Some even define respectable buffers from buildings that separate smokers from indoor places. Restaurants are smoke-free and lovely for eating food, which was the primary purpose of the restaurant to begin with. Workers and patrons are healthier and smokers can still smoke outside.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Citizens and decision-makers will realize that despite the perceived need to drive a car in an urban area, the destruction of doing so is simply too great to allow it in any urban area, even on streets that are supposedly not for pedestrians. They will realize that cars ruin any urban area where they are not exceptional, that if urban places permit car circulation then they endanger people and suppress the life of the community. Cars will continue being useful in rural places and for exceptional use in urban areas. Freight traffic will be restricted to certain delivery times in urban areas or replaced by more sophisticated delivery mechanisms. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;Conclusion&lt;/i&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We pulled off the full restaurant smoking ban in many places in as little as twenty years. Most cities will never ban cars before they evolve into something not identifiable as car. This is unfortunate, there are good reasons to disallow the car of the present as well as the future one that is electric and fully automated. The exercise and community arguments are the strongest for doing so, since we can't make space for communities or guarantee adequate exercise if cars remain in urban areas. Death and destruction that will continue for many years as well. We might as well define the car as an incompatible use now and find out how nice urban space can be without it.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-6747280989744093889?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/02/restaurant-smoking-analogy.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-7048476889709849499</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2011 23:36:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-02-01T15:36:20.408-08:00</atom:updated><title>Backstepping leads to confident crawling</title><description>&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TUiV0afqk8I/AAAAAAAAALc/QGqGNDxoeQ0/s1600/tmp.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I finally made some pivotal improvements to my road path drawing algorithm. All is not yet right, but the code is certainly prettier!&amp;nbsp; I'm posting a generated mess of paths with the hopes that I'll soon draw the same place clearly. Some significant problems that remain:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;I'm drawing the center line of all the paths and roads. It might be useful to know where the center is, but it's not worth the confusion. I want to give users blank roads and paths so they can make the maximal use of them, even if that means a non-symmetric use.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Some sidewalk and crosswalk data often exists and I treat them as paths, which makes a mess when I'm guessing how wide the roads are. Notice the arced sidewalks on the bridge and my road that is wider than them. I need to probably ignore all sidewalks that aren't dedicated paths. The path that goes under the railroad tracks in the bottom left corner is actually separated from the road by barriers, but I should probably ignore it anyway with the exception that the user will find a better way of allocating the entire right-of-way.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rendering errors still exist for some shapes. Notice the three Os in front of the building that represent the lanes of a parking lot. The one on the right has an erroneous loop, as do other roads shown here. I have to tack these one at a time and hope that one fix cures many problems without creating new ones.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;How should foot paths meet streets. Notice that the foot path in the bottom right meet the parking lot lands at their center lines. This is because I haven't told the paths to have any intersection relationship with the roads. I need to introduce the concept of a "neighborly intersection", so that different types of right of way can respect each others side boundaries. Paths and roads need to respect each other, while railroad tracks probably will never share an end node with a road or path, since they are fully incompatible modes of travel. Even a streetcar that went off street and back on could ignore the sides of the streets and render as if the sides of the street didn't exist.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TUiV5yNyV7I/AAAAAAAAALg/_NkVVAATzVQ/s1600/tmp2.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="459" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TUiV5yNyV7I/AAAAAAAAALg/_NkVVAATzVQ/s640/tmp2.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I feel a lot better about my progress since I stepped back and made some fundamental fixes and simplifications to my code. It's still slow go, but my movement is forward again, after some necessary back stepping.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-7048476889709849499?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/02/backstepping-leads-to-confident.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TUiV5yNyV7I/AAAAAAAAALg/_NkVVAATzVQ/s72-c/tmp2.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-6177982879936490037</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2011 21:43:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-01-24T13:43:58.828-08:00</atom:updated><title>Backstepping</title><description>I decided at some point last year that re-imagining a place to be carfree and transit happy was something that anyone should be able to do for their neighborhood given the right tools. The tools that I wanted to have don't exist or aren't available in the free and easy to use category. I figured that I could make some of those tools and add them to Sketchup, Google's freely available 3D modeling program. I would offer it has a plugin to Sketchup and create a web site to share and search submitted designs made with those tools. I dug into writing the plugin software, and I quickly hit roadblocks at every turn. Or road disfigurement I should say. I've spent months off and on playing with how to program roads to draw on a map, as I've highlighted in earlier posts. For some reason, other than it working perfectly and me moving on to something else, I've been stuck on this problem for a long time because roads intersect in complicated ways and my programming experience in the the graphics or trigonometry worlds is nonexistent.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I haven't given up on the software or the overall project, but I need to approach the software and a year of my work-time in a different manner, because it's starting to drive me crazy. Here's a list of my current problems, followed by potential solutions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Coding is no fun when you don't make progress.&lt;br /&gt;2. Coding all the time is not optimal for an urban planning student.&lt;br /&gt;3. Big projects that get blocked on the first problem are intimidating.&lt;br /&gt;4. Coding all day alone is lonely.&lt;br /&gt;5. Other people may have solved some of my coding problems but I haven't been eager to invest time into finding and possibly adapting their code to my problems.&lt;br /&gt;6. I have no support network of other urban planning software people.&lt;br /&gt;7. My urban planning peers can't help me and my programming peers can't help me through such a large challenge with coding assistance.&lt;br /&gt;8. I'm losing enthusiasm for the project before I've even completed a single part of it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Some potential solutions.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1. Step back and look at the problems. Done.&lt;br /&gt;2. Spend more time on researching the solutions to those problems instead of jumping right in to solve them.&lt;br /&gt;3. Read about loosely related but relevant topics, like functional programming, user interfaces, streetscape design, plumbing, or whatever, and taking good notes.&lt;br /&gt;4. Set up a diverse but consistent schedule--time to code, time to read, research, network, etc.&lt;br /&gt;5. Always look around online before you assume that nobody's thought about your problem.&lt;br /&gt;6. Take lots of breaks.&lt;br /&gt;7. Ignore artificial deadlines, but make your own deadlines.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;End Part 1 of Backstepping&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-6177982879936490037?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/01/backstepping.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-8987420170044032434</guid><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2011 19:24:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2011-01-23T15:22:10.148-08:00</atom:updated><title>Dear Secretary LaHood</title><description>I am a great admirer of your dedication to building high-speed rail in America. I am presently completing a pleasant train trip today which started in Oakland, CA and took me to stops in Denver, Chicago, Detroit/Windsor, Toronto, Québec City, and Montréal via Amtrak and Via Rail. Sadly, today's final leg of the trip from Montréal to Boston must be completed by Greyhound Bus because no direct or even same-day train service exists between these two large cities that are separated by a mere 300 miles. I spent the first half of the trip reading a year 2000 report on the possibilities of high speed rail along the corridor. I learned that the trip could be made in a modest five to six hours with non-high-speed rail speeds of up to 90 mph. I personally think that true high-speed rail along a straightened right-of-way would make more long-term sense, but a 90 mph train would be a great improvement over the current no train configuration. It is ironic that after making direct train connections between all the previous stops on my journey, with the exception of an odd missing link between Detroit and Windsor, that I should be forced to take a bus between Canada's largest city and Boston. Boston is a large metropolitan area with a fairly fast train connection to New York City and Washington DC, so a high speed connection that linked Montréal to Washington DC via Boston and New York would make sense.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now as we chug out of Burlington Vermont's airport Greyhound station (there is sadly no downtown station,) I am 3 hours into a 6 1/2 hour bus ride that cost nearly seventy dollars. The bus is fairly new and features intermittent wi-fi, a restroom, power outlets and a couple well-timed half-hour layovers so you can get a meal from the world's worst restaurant at the Burlington Airport and perhaps something better in White River Junction. Next time I will probably take the 11 hour train ride to New York, spend the night, and train to Boston the next day. Or more likely I will be forced to drive or fly because I have few friends as patient as the current one with whom I travel.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Having left Burlington's airport ten minutes ago, I see that we have returned to the airport to gather a late passenger. This was certainly a kind gesture on the part of Greyhound. I suppose a train wouldn't back up to pick someone up, but maybe that's for the benefit of everyone else on board. Probably the best solution is to create a more popular service with more frequency. Some train stations are poorly situated outside of downtown, but most are, thanks to our railroad history, in convenient downtown locations. There's naturally a compromise to be made when choosing between an airport and downtown train station, but I think defaulting to downtown and providing local transit to the airport makes more sense for the town's economy and land use patterns.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I won't say anything more about my Greyhound trip--my first ever--except to say that it's sad to try to travel responsibly and get stuck with a bus on a route that was previously covered by train service (until the 1960s.) I understand that funding high-speed rail must be incremental if it is to happen at all in this country. After all, with widespread Republican hatred of trains and government infrastructure spending (yourself excluded of course) it's lucky that we fund any rail at all. It would be reckless to fund high-speed rail in parallel nationwide, à la Interstate Highway System, so that the system could be widespread before 2050.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sincerely,&lt;br /&gt;Andy Likuski&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-8987420170044032434?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2011/01/dear-secretary-lehood.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-6903487104889915415</guid><pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2010 03:40:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-11-15T19:40:53.585-08:00</atom:updated><title>Union Square Post Mortem</title><description>Last week I submitted and presented my assignment on redoing the transportation for Union Square in Somerville, MA, given that a new light rail station is arriving there in 20&lt;strike&gt;14,&lt;/strike&gt;15. Here are the visual results of the effort:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH22a_T7VI/AAAAAAAAAKo/WkH-uHF3OPg/s1600/Prospect+VIew+from+south.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="460" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH22a_T7VI/AAAAAAAAAKo/WkH-uHF3OPg/s640/Prospect+VIew+from+south.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH2bGYAnkI/AAAAAAAAAKg/Y30GAVE3O04/s1600/Bird%2527s+eye+from+south.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="460" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH2bGYAnkI/AAAAAAAAAKg/Y30GAVE3O04/s640/Bird%2527s+eye+from+south.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH2p7v7E3I/AAAAAAAAAKk/vbGyfWpCO-E/s1600/Bus+Right+of+Way.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="459" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH2p7v7E3I/AAAAAAAAAKk/vbGyfWpCO-E/s640/Bus+Right+of+Way.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH2-E-5UUI/AAAAAAAAAKs/GYwrUr_G63M/s1600/Northwest+look.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="460" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH2-E-5UUI/AAAAAAAAAKs/GYwrUr_G63M/s640/Northwest+look.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH3JiK0woI/AAAAAAAAAKw/BXdg2QqjJfo/s1600/Market+View.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="460" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH3JiK0woI/AAAAAAAAAKw/BXdg2QqjJfo/s640/Market+View.png" width="640" /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;The images are pretty decent. This is a mix of a lot of visual clues from different sources: Google Earth provides the underlying map and stretched 3D buildings, my software provided the road network, Sketchup's 3D wharehouse provided treet, streetcars, fruit stands, people, cars, etc, and I modeled a few things like the new buildings and market stands. And yes, that is Homer Simpson's car in the third shot, for all you discontinuity fans out there.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;I'll admit that my software didn't contribute much to this project. In fact the roads it made were in places incomplete and in other places needed to be stretched to fit the actual area. Union Square itself had to be completely redrawn since I wasn't interested in the existing roads. Unfortunately, my program at the time made each road segment its own component, so I had to edit each component to put details on it. I've learned from this mistake and now the roads render as one single entity that isn't even part of a group. Whether one should make the roads a separate group or not is still up for debate, as is whether one should add streetcars, bike lanes, etc to the roads group itself or just stick them on top of the road group. You won't care if you've never used Sketchup. And that's what the software must assume.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;During the project, I struggled to lay down streetcar track. First I downloaded track and tried to make it fit together around curving roads. That was a huge disaster that I won't expose a user too. I finally gave in and just drew appropriately spaced lines for the tracks, but even that was a huge challenge. What I need is to let the user hit a but or drag a panel onto the road that represents a streetcar track. The panel should be adjust to fit the road correctly, and then be stretchable to any length and follow the curve of the road. That applies to streetcar tracks, bus lanes, bike lanes and any other right-of-way.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;I desperately need to make a tool that constrains movement to the XY plane. Sketchup is simply asinine in this respect. It let's you constrain movement to one axis, but heaven forbid you want do move something diagonally across the street. It assumes you want to adjust the height of the object. I literally found myself with cars 20 feet in the air after I thought I was dragging them to another street. I want to constrain all dragging to the ground unless the user specifies that they want to lift something in the air or put it underground. In the meantime I have to tack along the X and Y axes to go diagonal.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;I found that creating stretched buildings in Google Earth isn't impossible, but it's not much fun either. I don't really want to expose my users to that. Hopefully I can automatically download the buildings already modeled in their neighborhood from the Google Earth API. The best bet for the other buildings is to give the user an easy tool for building modeling. Tell them to grab the building tool and then trace the satellite image of the building footprint. This will take a face and expand it twenty feet in the air to approximate any building.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;As I've planned before, the user will need a host of pre-loaded 3D objects, like streetcars, bikes, people, and trees, so that they can minimize trips to the 3D warehouse. The 3D warehouse is fun to use, but inexperienced users need a simple set of objects at their finger tips.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;I backed up the Union Square rendering throughout the process, so I can present building Union Square as an animated example of how to use the software. Of course, this project didn't use the software, so this demo might make a good "look how hard this is without my software!"&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;I learned lots of other things about how to write a good report. Report generation comes much later in the game, but at least these assignments are filling my head with possibilities.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-6903487104889915415?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/11/union-square-post-mortem.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TOH22a_T7VI/AAAAAAAAAKo/WkH-uHF3OPg/s72-c/Prospect+VIew+from+south.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-3117561108567779468</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 17:14:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-11-05T10:14:47.616-07:00</atom:updated><title>Flatwork Base design</title><description>&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TNQ7VXU-XfI/AAAAAAAAAKc/KSv-95JQ3KY/s1600/Union+Square.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="396" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TNQ7VXU-XfI/AAAAAAAAAKc/KSv-95JQ3KY/s640/Union+Square.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Here's a 2-D design of Union Square so called. My book calls this a Flatwork Base.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-3117561108567779468?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/11/flatwork-base-design.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TNQ7VXU-XfI/AAAAAAAAAKc/KSv-95JQ3KY/s72-c/Union+Square.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-649301092899736546</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2010 00:52:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-11-01T17:52:20.719-07:00</atom:updated><title>Two months later...my first user experience</title><description>I started writing my thesis software a couple months ago. The initial plan can be viewed &lt;a href="http://sites.google.com/a/likuski.org/rescape/initial-software-plans"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but you won't get much out of it. I struggled for the last two months trying to figure out the best way to render imported road data into Sketchup to create street shapes upon which one might try redrawing their streets. It looks something like this:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9Wc81fQmI/AAAAAAAAAKI/v9_bb05Qvn4/s1600/demo.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="199" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9Wc81fQmI/AAAAAAAAAKI/v9_bb05Qvn4/s320/demo.png" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Not bad, right? Well it took me a couple months to figure out the geometry to make the roads intersect cleanly. I'm no expert in linear algebra and making two dimensional shapes intersect cleanly is difficult without any good understanding of the subject. As you can see, both roads and foot paths are rendered, and the roads are rendered according to the data provided by the life-saving openstreetmap.org. Openstreetmap.org contains a wealth of other data, including building footprints, which I'm leaving alone for now.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It happens that I have a homework project in my transportation class that asks me to improve upon the plan for redevelopment of Union Square in Somerville, MA. Union Square is receiving a light rail station and needs a little face lift. Unfortunately for the city of Somerville that means as of now a copy/paste solution of the successful Davis Square a couple miles away. Davis is chalk full of restaurants, bars, and has great transit, but the streets tear it up like some sort of perverse inverted pretzel:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9YV2OlplI/AAAAAAAAAKM/mMhtWDs4I2k/s1600/Davis.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9YV2OlplI/AAAAAAAAAKM/mMhtWDs4I2k/s320/Davis.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/0f/Davis_sq_aug_2006.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/0/0f/Davis_sq_aug_2006.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This six or seven way intersection is the pride of Somerville. It was  revitalized in the 1980s when the red line T subway was extended from  Harvard Square. To be fair, it does look pretty good from certain  angles, especially when you have ice cream.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm determined to make Union Square a better story than Davis Square. It's my first opportunity to try out my software, and so far my software hasn't done be much good. I was able to load all the streets I needed with some error in the intersections that I had to correct.&amp;nbsp; After a hour or more of edits I got the Sketchup model into this primitive state:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9bdUXu6wI/AAAAAAAAAKQ/JUadY7cLkVc/s1600/Union+Square.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="396" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9bdUXu6wI/AAAAAAAAAKQ/JUadY7cLkVc/s640/Union+Square.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;If I were an inexperienced Sketchup user I'd already be out of luck. The white areas are the streets that I want to work on. Union Square is the top area and Inman Square is below. I want to pedestrianize Prospect Street which connects the two squares and will host the Green Line light rail station (about 1/3 of the way from Union Square down to Prospect Street, where the faint railroad track passes through.) Had I been a user trying to decide which streets I wanted to focus on, I wouldn't have known how to change the color of the of certain streets. That's because each road segment is actually a separate object that needs to be edited and recolored separately. I haven't been able to decide if I want to make all the streets a single object, for ease of editing by the user, or leave them as separate objects. The former is more intuitive for the user, but is more prone to error. If one segment of the unified streets were missing or deleted, it would make all the streets lose their "face" meaning the surface that holds the color.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Unfortunately, there will be many times were the users wants to edit the shape of the street, either because it didn't render correctly from the downloaded street data, or because they want to expand the street surface, as I did for Union Square on top. So, from this early vantage point, it appears that I need a few helpful tools for the user:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A highlight road segment tour. The user simple clicks or rolls over the roads of interest and the tool highlights them a different color than the others. This only works if the roads are different segments, since a unified road would be the same color unless demarcation lines were drawn.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;An expand or contract road tool. I always knew I would need this, but now it's that much more obvious. The user should be able to draw a line around any piece of road to expand the road surface. This is standard behavior if the road segments aren't groups, but needs to be done programatically if they are.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9en8BY9iI/AAAAAAAAAKU/fLN_YYGzHYk/s1600/Picture+3.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9en8BY9iI/AAAAAAAAAKU/fLN_YYGzHYk/s200/Picture+3.png" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9fFRzpmqI/AAAAAAAAAKY/W0gG5V-okpE/s1600/Picture+4.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9fFRzpmqI/AAAAAAAAAKY/W0gG5V-okpE/s200/Picture+4.png" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-649301092899736546?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/11/two-months-latermy-first-user.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TM9Wc81fQmI/AAAAAAAAAKI/v9_bb05Qvn4/s72-c/demo.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-8186580754711803078</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2010 14:01:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-09-14T07:01:37.567-07:00</atom:updated><title>Amendments</title><description>In my privous software outline, I left out a couple important components. One is that the designer needs to incorporate trip times and travel speeds into the plans. It should be clear that a new streetcar line will perform well in moving people, not just in reclaiming the street. Similarly car trip times should be estimated, comparing the travel time in reality to what it would be in the model. I also forgot to mention traffic lights for intersections that give street cars priority. I have to decide what level of detail will be offered. Obviously the user can go and get objects from 3D wharehouse, but I'm not really that interested in offering garbage cans and newspaper vendors. Of course I can organize the wharehouse offerings by streetscape subject.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-8186580754711803078?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/09/amendments.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-2291039214673210412</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2010 00:44:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-09-13T17:44:00.581-07:00</atom:updated><title>How to start a software based master's thesis</title><description>The first step can probably be in Sketchup if I can observe the Google Earth load event. If not, it will have to begin in Google Maps.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Interactive Step 1: What area are you interested in modeling? Select it.&lt;br /&gt;Process 1:&lt;br /&gt;User selects the area of the map in Google maps.&lt;br /&gt;The selected coordinate box is sent to a provider of road data. This may be a GIS server or possibly the Google Maps API. The server returns the road data.&lt;br /&gt;Sketchup is launched. A Sketchup plugin imports the selected map is imported into Sketchup. It will probably be necessary to import zoomed in maps from Google Earth that make up the user's selection.&lt;br /&gt;A Sketchup plugin observes the map import and in turen imports the road data as narrow 3D lines. A default width of 10 feet may be appropriate if no data is available about the width. Matching the road data width will be challenging. It may be necessary for the user to pull each road to it's correct width. This isn't too much to ask.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sketchup now controls an HTML page that further guides the user.&lt;br /&gt;Interactive Step 2: Would you like add more mapping area to Sketchup? If yes return the user to the web browser to select a new area from Google Maps. Repeat process 1. Alternatively the user may want to start over. If no than the user is ready to modify the streets. Show the user how to pull out a sample piece of street. You can probably just bring up a little screenshot video to show them how.&lt;br /&gt;Process 2: Observe all the street stretches (streets will be identified as streets using attributes. Do not allow stretching along the Z plane. This should prevent mistakes. Offer the option to restore the street to it's original if the user screws up.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Interactive Step 3: When the user is satisfied with their stretches, it's time to apply 3D surfaces to the streets. These will be selectable from a neatly organized set up panels with clear descriptions. &lt;br /&gt;Process 3:&lt;br /&gt;The user should be able to drag instances to the street where they want them located. The panels should snap. Normal sketchup copy/paste and move/paste operations will be supported, but Z axis constrained.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Optional Step 4: They should also be able to add metros at a fixed level on the negative Z access. The metro need not be more than track and trains, though showing tunnels should be reasonable. The underground metro will need to be drawn with a line tool that is Z constrained. It should transform to metro tunnel as the lines are drawn. The lines should be converted to double track metro. More metro lines should be possible at other Z levels or alongside.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Step 5:&amp;nbsp; The user can always return to steps 3 and 4. The next step is to add streetscape elements, such as lighting, trees, and streetcars. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That's about it for the streets! Building importation and stretching is tricky. It may be fairly easy if building elevations are available in GIS, but I'm not sure how common this is.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Once streets and buildings are setup. It's time to do ridership analysis, traffic analysis, and economic and true cost analysis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Step 1: Whether or not temporary car lanes were placed in the model by the user, the user should write about the changed traffic patterns. Offer the user plenty of guidance.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Step 2: Using other city transit data, the user should be guided through the process of making ridership estimates for the transit service. They should speak here about number of trips claimed from buses and cars. Again, plenty of guidance is needed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Step 3: Traditional economic benefits. Use guidance from other plans to guide the user. Check out the Oakland streetcar plan.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Step 4: Full cost economic analysis. Guide the user through this analysis as well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Step 5: Report generator. Give the user export tools to generate a report. Give the user information about where to send the report--media, politicians. The report should be posted to the carfree-cities site as should the sketchup data. The user may have to tag the project based on the location they want it identified with (if the location engine is anything more than lat/lon)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Next step, illustrations&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-2291039214673210412?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/09/how-to-start-software-based-masters.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-6127737760800149377</guid><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2010 20:23:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-06-25T13:23:06.715-07:00</atom:updated><title>The premise of my work</title><description>The premise of the work I am to do as an urban planner is that there is a formula for transforming a particular urban district or limited combination of districts into a much better place by introducing comprehensive fast transit, removing private automobile use,&amp;nbsp; and modularizing goods delivery. I have concluded that in virtually any place in North America there must be a configuration of the district(s) that is vastly superior to the existing configuration of the roads and their usages. There must also be a short sequence of implementation phases to transform the current state of the district(s) to the improved state. The variety of intermediate steps are limited, but I think one major possibility is to halve the width of the road dedicated to cars and reallocate that space for transit, pedestrians, and cyclists (hereafter car-free usage). A second intermediate step is to remove goods delivery by trucks in favor of above-ground metro freight (on the streetcar tracks) or below grown metro freight service. This would limit vehicle use on the roads to service-based vehicles, such as utilities, emergency vehicles, and special deliveries that could not be done with modularized shipping (e.g. a crane). During these intermediate phases the streetscape can be optimized in form and function for car-free usage.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In order to prove my ultimate car-free configuration superior to the current state of the district(s), I must justify the transition with traditional economic modeling. This is unfortunate, because the full-cost accounting (i.e. social and environmental costs) and qualitative benefits will more than justify any project. But the reality of our society forces me to consider traditional consumption-based economics. Fortunately, I believe that economic superiority will be able to underwrite car-free configurations. Carbon taxes will be among the greatest assistants.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One helpful shortcut that I now realize is that I'm not concerned with changing where roads are nor the buildings that stand alongside them. Developers and business people will likely optimize buildings for car-free streets. Multistory houses may or may not have their first floor converted to storefronts. One story buildings may be rebuilt to supply upper floor housing. It really helps to realize that I am not interested in such things. I care about street and rail networks above all else. When you get these right you tend to get correspondingly good practices in building.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In a future post I would like to demonstrate the intermediate phases of street redevelopment to transform to a car-free district. Right now I'm working on the "district" around my university, Tufts. By tracing the major streets on top of Google Earth snapshots in Google Sketchup, I was able to realize what really matters, and what doesn't. The primary streets of the district matter, the residential neighborhoods and the university facilities can be left alone. Seeing the primary roads outlined in Sketchup made me realize what is the essential skeleton of a district. The next step is to identify the inputs and outputs of the district, meaning the roads and rails that connect to other places, and explore what is conveyed over these boundaries. I don't mean to sound overly modular, but converting a district to a better form is so complicated that you have to simplify it somehow. Identifying the key right-of-way seems to be the best way to do it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Another reason I'm so interested in the phases of development is that I want to be able to offer design steps to people who want to redo their own district, and thus propel the car-free cities movement. Using Joel Crawford's Carfree Design Guide, one can see what the best design practices are. I really need his help in laying out the redesign steps.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-6127737760800149377?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/06/premise-of-my-work.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-910388461608467962</guid><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jun 2010 17:58:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-09-14T10:48:18.197-07:00</atom:updated><title></title><description>&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TBUaDvkXhTI/AAAAAAAAAJ4/7F_c9vZqgS4/s1600/Picture+2.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="202" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TBUaDvkXhTI/AAAAAAAAAJ4/7F_c9vZqgS4/s400/Picture+2.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.panoramio.com/photos/original/6772417.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="300" src="http://www.panoramio.com/photos/original/6772417.jpg" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This free write is dedicated to a very dear and pressing topic to me. How do we visualize the street changes that are needed on streets across North America? I was walking on College Avenue in Somerville from Davis Square, a red line subway location to Tufts, my graduate school campus, and beyond for a few blocks. I've fantasized about a proposed remodeling of this street as my thesis project--at least others have told me it should be a thesis project. As I walked down the long stretch of College that flanks Tufts' southeast side, I couldn't help seeing the street that I wanted in its place. I actually saw Montpellier, France. I saw the streets not of asphalt but of a tannish tone, made of smooth paving stones. I saw the street as a grand boulevard of pedestrians, even though it is only about 50 feet wide. I saw the glistening rails down the center where the streetcars swish by. I imagined the trees that already line the sidewalks being larger and arching over the entirety of the width to cool the street. The cement sidewalks melted away because they weren't needed. The whole thing was a sidewalk, or more simply a walk. The parked vehicles likewise ceased to be; no vehicles would barrel up and down the street. The place turned into a European paradise.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I've been thinking mightily about how to empower people to revisualize their streets. I don't think there is some simple tool that I can put on the web to enable one to redesign their street. LIkewise I don't have the power to redo a lot of neighborhoods myself and create a 3D walk-through. The main reason I don't is that I don't live in these places, so how can I say how to redo them? I have to give people a reference model though, so that they can see what I see when they look at their streets. How do I develop imaginations? Where's the pair of googles? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The software engineer in me wants to find a software solution, and I don't doubt that therein lies a bulk of the solution. The dreamer in me wants to write stories and draw pictures. There must be a solution that transcends both these perspectives.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We can't give Americans Europe, partly because many of them would reject being recast as Europe. I don't want to give them Main Street either, because that isn't a carfree street with streetcars. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm reminded of the game Roller Coaster Tycoon. You'd design an amusement park and the people would infiltrate its paths and attractions. We used to cause mayhem to the people by building dysfunctional roller coasters that launched them into the lagoon. We'd block the entrance to the park so that people couldn't leave. It was fun to see what they did when they were blocked. That's how I feel about College Avenue. I want to be God and just block it to see what all those cars would do. I want to see how many more pedestrians and bikers would use a street blocked to cars. I want to see who would get on a streetcar that passed ever five&amp;nbsp; minutes and moved them a mile in just a few minutes. SimMyCity, that's what I want. Will Wright, are you listening? But this is all just basic transportation simulation, so it mustn't be sufficient. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But back to visualizing, what do I do? Do I walk around Davis Square with a clipboard and some pretty pictures? I'd be laughed at by most people, were I to suggest that College Avenue should change. Or , more likely, I'd be met with apathy and disinterest. Who even thinks about these things anyway? Well, I think there is something to be said for the use of filter books. in the movie, A Talking Picture, the professor shows her daughter how ancients sites use to look with a book of plastic overlays over the present day site. That's what I imagine doing in Sketchup--take the orignal sight and then start folding down the overlays. That would most closely match what goes on in my head as I walk down College Ave.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-910388461608467962?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/06/this-free-write-is-dedicated-to-very.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TBUaDvkXhTI/AAAAAAAAAJ4/7F_c9vZqgS4/s72-c/Picture+2.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-6752613016406887714</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 18:41:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-06-01T11:41:24.561-07:00</atom:updated><title>Gateways between urban and greenspace</title><description>&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU4PCK5t6I/AAAAAAAAAIw/mLNAOvOgp_8/s1600/Picture+19.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU4PCK5t6I/AAAAAAAAAIw/mLNAOvOgp_8/s320/Picture+19.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;I took a bike ride around the Middlesex Fells Reservation, which is a  large green space with a sizable pond and beautiful 8 lane interstate running through it. It has nice walking and mountain biking paths, and also hosts a zoo, ice rink, nature center, etc. Parts of the space are quite lovely, with only the low roil of traffic in the distance to disturb the serenity. Unfortunately the gateways to this reservation of land is on hidden neighborhood streets and via busy roads that are unfriendly to bikes and pedestrians (Such as Woodland Rd. and S. Border Rd.) The type of gateway that is lacking is one that connects a business district or densely populated neighborhood. I can make a safe assumption that few people that live in Medford, Cambridge, and Somerville, which are all dense urban areas to the south, have ever visited this reservation by foot or car. Bus service is also poor, which I can attest to from direct experience trying to reach the park from just a couple miles south.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It's perfectly understanding why protected open spaces do not lie in close proximity to urban centers. The whole purpose of a preserved open space is to protect an area that was far enough from urban areas to have been left alone, or had an important water source or geographic feature to discourage development. But the fact that this open space is so close to dense urban areas suggests that there ought to be some inviting gateways from the urban space to the green space, so that all the people who live densely will actually be encouraged to access it without a car.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU6zcaPvCI/AAAAAAAAAI4/Gi3cero7ABA/s1600/Picture+20.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU6zcaPvCI/AAAAAAAAAI4/Gi3cero7ABA/s320/Picture+20.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU9QdSkQqI/AAAAAAAAAJA/Bvb9YtmIqAM/s1600/Picture+21.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU9QdSkQqI/AAAAAAAAAJA/Bvb9YtmIqAM/s320/Picture+21.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Davis Square in Somerville is densely populated and serves as a popular destination due to a Red Line subway station, it's proximity to Tufts University, and the fact that it is two subway stops from Harvard but much less commercialized in feel (which all the cool kids appreciate.) The A on the map is Davis Square, and B is the closest point to the reservation, a whopping 2 1/2 miles away. But for the walker or biker, there is no friendly way of transport, but for snaking one's way through a maze of residential streets, and then still must they content with crossing three numbered highways (the thick yellow ones, that represent some degree of misery to traverse comfortably.) You could argue that there isn't any real reason why Davis Square should be comfortably connected to the closest significant green space in the region. After all, why would people that live in an urban environment without a car desire access to peace and tranquility? You might instead agree that access is appropriate, but why not just rely on public transit. After all, that town of Winchester looks pretty sizable, isn't there a convenient bus to get there? In fact it is possible to reach the B marker on buses, one just needs to allow 30 minutes and one transfer to get there, not to mention up to 30 minutes wait for the first bus to come. Now, I'm not saying I've never taken two buses for thirty minutes to arrive at a destination 2 1/2 miles away, but it certainly isn't on my list of favorite things to do. And, just in case you were wondering, this is probably the easiest part of the park to get to. If you want to go the popular Spy Pond (with zoo, ice rink, etc) try going to Boston first. It takes over an hour, two subways, and a bus, to arrive at Spy Pond from Davis Square (distance: 4.8 miles).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU9_-vCeoI/AAAAAAAAAJI/tREjZfJ9Gio/s1600/Picture+22.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU9_-vCeoI/AAAAAAAAAJI/tREjZfJ9Gio/s320/Picture+22.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;I'm also well aware that transit service is based on demand, at least in theory. In reality good transit service creates demand--if you see that a subway goes to a nice large park you're more likely to want to visit that park. When I lived briefly in Montreal, I would look at the subway map on the weekends to find out which green spaces I could access from a subway station. A lot of people use metro maps as a destination guide. But fewer people look at a map and then decide to take two buses to get to a green space that's 2 1/2 miles away.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAVHuwhO2II/AAAAAAAAAJY/1YeOAtnQlIk/s1600/Picture+24.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAVHuwhO2II/AAAAAAAAAJY/1YeOAtnQlIk/s320/Picture+24.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAVKPylV4XI/AAAAAAAAAJg/FYdDx0wY_-E/s1600/Picture+25.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAVKPylV4XI/AAAAAAAAAJg/FYdDx0wY_-E/s320/Picture+25.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;We need to start thinking about our population centers with good transit, like Davis Square, and figure out how to create inviting gateways to the nice places that people should be able to visit easily. In the case of Davis Square to Middlesex Fells Reservation, there are some fairly obvious routes that would serve large populations and connect several urban centers with the reservation. To the left are the existing passenger rail and bike routes relevant to connecting Davis Square to the reservation (the Green Line is due to arrive in 2014, and I may be missing a couple of dedicated bike/pedestrian paths, but probably not important ones.) Notice that there is actually a lot of passenger rail service in the vicinity. The purple lines are commuter rail service, so only run about once every hour or two.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are a couple key connections obviously missing to make it easy to go from Davis Square to the reservation. The first is an east-west rail connection between Davis Square, the Green Line extension and the Orange Line. Such a service could probably be effectively done by a streetcar with dedicated right of way that arrives at frequent intervals, say every 5 to 10 minutes. The other problem is that the 93 highway represents the ideas route to the reservation, since it splits it in half. If only there was some justification for putting a rail route along the 93 highway. If only there were ten of thousands of people that needed to travel that corridor to get to Boston in an efficient and reliable way. The solutions are to create an urban ring line that connection the various rail lines that extend from Boston (located 5 miles south) and to use the center lanes of the interstates for passenger rail service. Both of these solutions add massive numbers of riders to passenger rail system, and happen to connect places like Middlesex Fells Reservation and Davis Square with easy reliable connections.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I don't want to suggest that rail is the solution to all of our gateway problems. It would be just as well to connect Davis Square to the green spaces that surround it with more bike/pedestrian paths. But to do so we can't rely on abandoned railroads. We need start identifying residential streets and arterial roads that can be converted to non car use. There is enough redundancy in most road systems that this should be desirable. Even should a residential road be split in half, with one side dedicated to walking and pedestrians and the other for local car access, we could accomplish a lot. The walking/biking path could be separated by small trees or a nice fence or wall. Cars wishing to access the driveway on the path side of the street would be infrequent, and the right to park a car in those driveways could be purchased and removed by the city. Eventually all driveways on the path side of the street could be eliminated, creating a car-free corridor where all houses still have road access for deliveries and emergencies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAVTFel9JJI/AAAAAAAAAJw/X3RSKTsb8-c/s1600/Picture+26.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="353" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAVTFel9JJI/AAAAAAAAAJw/X3RSKTsb8-c/s640/Picture+26.png" width="640" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This rendering is incomplete, but one can image that cars would be limited to a 15' wide road, and the remaining 15' could be given to bicycles pedestrians and a protective green strip. Only cars that had business with the houses on the street would be allowed access and great care would have to be taken crossing the pedestrian path into driveways. The cross-path access would be eliminated as soon as the city could take away the homeowner's right to use the driveway for parking. Then the homeowner could reallocate the driveway to better uses. The 15' wide road could be divided into 10' of driving space and 5' of parking on the right side, if the residents on the street desired that.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In summary, there are all kinds of significant steps we can take to improve transit, pedestrian, and bike access between urban centers and green spaces. All of these measures would likely be economically beneficial to the city and homeowners, and would certainly increase quality of life and improve the city's environmental performance. I'll write further on this subject in subsequent posts.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-6752613016406887714?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/06/gateways-between-urban-and-greenspace.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media='http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/' url='http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_2AP5BgFnoxg/TAU4PCK5t6I/AAAAAAAAAIw/mLNAOvOgp_8/s72-c/Picture+19.png' height='72' width='72'/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-2721521586822987641</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 02:56:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-06-01T07:41:03.261-07:00</atom:updated><title>Writing, it's official</title><description>As part of my graduate degree in Urban Planning, I've enrolled in a writing class called Effective Writing for Public Communication. To date I haven't been a very good public communicator by means of writing, since no one reads this blog that I write on urban planning. I don't advertise my blog and I haven't published any of my urban planning work with exception of posting papers on obscure URLs that no one will ever find. This isn't from lack of self-confidence. I simply don't have a large enough body of work to justify putting together a fancy web page to host it. Thus I have limited most of my outreach to this semi-private blog. As I dig into my first summer and soon second year of graduate school, I will amass several research projects, many design ideas of public space improvements, and hopefully a comprehensive plan or two about important places where I dwell. It is therefore inevitable that I combine my blog writing and all the projects I do into some online form that is destined for public consumption. The writing class will help me present my work with good language, making persuasive and well-reasoned explanations about my work, which primarily advocates car-free neighborhood redevelopment and superb transit to serve neighborhoods and cities. In addition to publishing my work online, the course will also help me become more connected in the planning community, media, and government, by encouraging me to become active with editorials, comments, and submission of my urban plans to those who will listen. Thus there is the online portfolio and the aggressive solicitation of ideas that together represent my written output.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I have never struggled greatly to write, but that may be the result of mediocre standards. My vocabulary, word usage, and sentence structure are deficient by my own evaluation because I enjoy the study of the English language and foreign languages, but don't consider myself to be well-read nor greatly practiced at writing. I think the course will give me the needed trainer that forces me to do the exercises that I want to be doing on my own. Already since beginning the course last week I have been writing in my blogs more frequently to complete a 4-7 times-per-week journal requirement. Interestingly, I have mostly been writing in my blog about learning German, rather than writing in my urban planning or personal blogs. I don't at this time know what I'm going to get out of the class. I expect to absorb many good writing exercises and techniques that I keep in mind as I write in the future. I find that in most new activities in which I partake, I am keen to what learning tools emerge to help me with that subject. I expect I'll latch on to several tools that help me increase my vocabulary while decreasing verbosity. I'll also learn to observe my writing as an outsider, reviewing drafts frequently to be able to make more objective evaluations of my writing's usefulness to myself and others.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I need to at this point come up with three options for final writing projects for the course. The first that comes to mind relates my project to make the Tufts campus car-free as well as College Avenue between Davis Square and the anticipated Green Line station at Tufts. Pedestrianization of these student-heavy corridors would be aided by a modern streetcar that would traverse College Avenue and a critical street of Tufts, such as Professor's Row. Therefore my writing project would be an initial letter to the president of Tufts, the mayors of Somerville and Medford, or to all three. I call this project Car-free Tufts. A second possible writing project is an editorial that describes to the public why the Urban Ring needs to be built now and why it is both advantageous and necessary from an economic perspective. The Urban Ring is the decades old idea to connect the inner suburbs and neighborhoods of Boston by a circular rail line that extends through Chelsey, Medford, Roxbury, and East Boston. My final idea is a loud call to arms for pedestrians and bikers to rise up and protest the spatial and environmental injustice that they suffer from the automobile. I will write an editorial or magazine article describing what tools pedestrians and bikers have for taking the streets away from cars, such as public displays of protest, pressure on elected officials, and legal action that opposes car usage from an environmental and health perspective. I call this project Car-free Movement.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I like all of these ideas equally, and having just thought of them I do not yet have a favorite. I have a lot of knowledge about each subject already researched, except for the third option. I expect I will have to do a large amount of research for each--finding economic justifications for the first two and figuring out how to frame the arguments for all three. The benefits of the Car-free Tufts and Urban Ring projects is that they will help me develop my ideas for getting either one implemented. The benefits of the Car-free Movement project is that it will help me develop ideas about how I want to make the car-free movement a visible policy issue, which it certainly isn't right now. The length of the Car-free Tufts and Car-free Movement writings would likely be around eight to ten pages, since each will have to go into a fair amount of detail. The Urban Ring writing, being an editorial, would be limited to a couple pages.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-2721521586822987641?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/05/writing-its-official.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-425468777350413717</guid><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 16:16:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-05-26T09:16:17.160-07:00</atom:updated><title></title><description>What's the mental effect of not having to ride in a car, to not fly over the ugly overpasses and avoid sitting in bumper-to-bumper traffic? Does $6.75 for a one-way forty minute ride on the commuter train, with my bike, sound like a better deal than 25 minutes on highways in a car in light traffic or worse? I'll happily pay to look out the train window and catch a glimpse of Walden Pond at dusk, or simply see trees wizz by 15 feet from my window without the pain of billboards, off ramps, and 4 to 10 lanes of asphalt chaos.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If I have to bike a few miles to and from the train station, I'll probably enjoy some of that ride. In winter, I may give myself time to walk on the snowy sidewalk, or I may have to give in to a cab when it's really brutal out and no bus service exists.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What if everyone picked up a backpack and took their car keys off the chain? What if trains were overwhelmed with new permanent riders, people who simply perferred this new simplified lifestyle? We can have this today with one big nudge. Just a few illuminations--that cars are the raskels wasting most of our energy, whether by pushing a ton of steal around or permittimg sprawling developments that allow for big wasteful things. What if we told concerned parents that the reason their kids can't play in front of the house, or walk to school with their friends, is because of those cars that the parents themselves drive. It is their cars that make the streets unsafe, not the passer-through or the neighbor's teenage son. Would they then still feel like driving, or would they consider walking to a train and asking for steetcars?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-425468777350413717?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/05/whats-mental-effect-of-not-having-to.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-7705301657734378387</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2010 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-04-12T06:20:17.705-07:00</atom:updated><title>Boston to New Orleans on the right-of-way</title><description>I've been riding the Amtrak Crescent train from New York to New Orleans since 2pm yesterday, and I arrive at 7:30pm tonight in New Orleans, with an extra hour thrown in for the time change. Including the trip on the Northeast Corridor train from Boston, my total train time logged 35 hours. I was a bit disappointed to find that the Amtrak cars on all the East Coast trains are a lackluster variety that resemble an airplane fuselage. The long-distance cars like mine offer more legroom, but the cars are low to the ground and quite bumpy. In reading Wikipedia I learned that these cares were manufactured in the late seventies and early eighties in two batches, so now thirty years later they are antequated. The windows are small and rectangular, rather than the larger sightseeing windows that you find on the California Amtrak trains, which upgraded to double decker cars around 1991. Neither compares well to Canada's ViaRail, which I remember being much quiter and somoother. It was often the case on ViaRail that all you heard was the squeeking of the car connectors, especially when the ventilation system shut off, which seemed frequent. So in summary, it would be nice to see Amtrak update its fleeet, and I'm going to read a .pdf on its fleet upgrade plans as soon as I have broader band.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We're just pullling into Laurel, Missippi, whose stop is a somewhat modern looking brick building with a big Amtrak sign in front, as if the town itself wanted no part in promoting the train station. Mississippi and Alabama have a lot of trees and are flat, so it's interesting to arrive in a town with some cleared land. Occasionally, especially, in Georgia, I got a glimpse of some plantation style homes, but generally the properties by the tracks are quite humble, as are the towns through which we pass. The people on the train are diverse, but almost entirely black or white. Most are from the South and the accents are present but rarely overwhelming. I didn't interact with much of anyone, except my seatmate, who was an African American woman in her 40s or 50s traveling from Delaware to visit home in Mississippi. The most interesting remarks I overheard was the woman in front of me, saying she was going home to Mississippi because a friend or relative's husband had been killed when beaten in his home by robbers--the victim was in his sixties. I also heard and elderly gentlemen exclaim that he just saw a movie in a theater for the first time since 1993, when he saw Forrest Gump. I hope it was as good a movie.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;More on the nature of things--I find that my fellow passengers are middle to lower class here in coach. Many of their dietary habits are poor, some of their manners are as well, such as letting there cell phones go off on a frequent interval. But they are all friendly and the mood is amicable. At first I was disappointed to see no tourists like myself, although I do have business in New Orleans. Then I decided that people using a train to simply get somewhere is a wonderful thing to experience. Most people seemed to enjoy the journey. There are only two sleeper cars on the train, which was also disappointing, since I noticed them sell out well in advance online. This points to the humble service of the train, whose main purpose is to get people to small towns whence they migrated for city jobs. But it would be nice to see the train better accomodate more economic classes of passenger. I would certainly take the sleeping car if I were traveling with a companion. The coach car can be a delicate balance of enjoying the company and being bothered by people's home habits that they bring to a public space. I still think of the train as a luxury, and it can be tough sometimes to see it as commodity travel like the airlines are. I think some of this could be solved if we have long distance high-speed rail or sub-high speeed rail, as they seem to have throughout Western Europe. The only way to really be able to pick a more granular level of luxury though is to have much more service, to get tenfold more people using trains. I think this can happen in the U.S., Canada, and Mexico. If we make the networks comprehensive and zippy, and give good transit connections in the city, we can make the passenger railroad something with a very public face. We also need the rental car market to evolve so that people going to rural places can get a car painlessly, without having to worry about rental car agencies at small town stations being closed on weekends. We should be able to reseve onnline and swipe a card to go. But that's the least of my worries. Mainly I want to see our train system grow on the backs of environmental concerns, desire to have a high quality travel experience, and springboard off a spiraling oil costs.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-7705301657734378387?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/04/boston-to-new-orleans-on-right-of-way.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-2646644522496881292</guid><pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2010 03:27:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-04-05T18:49:28.624-07:00</atom:updated><title>From advocate to nag</title><description>One of the hardest parts about supporting transit is traveling to a destination with other people. With one companion who knows me well, it doesn't feel like nagging to suggest taking transit over driving. Once the number in the party reaches three, though, or another variable like transporting a potluck contribution comes into play, I inevitably get the "let's just drive" interjection. When the trip obviously favors transit, such as a destination downtown,  I can often dismiss the suggestion. It's the trickier ones like tonight--subway downtown and commuter train beyond that, where I really have a tough time defeating the loathsome auto. I can't say transit is faster, or more convenient, and the argument that we'll spend more quality face-to-face time together and do something in line with my most impassioned beliefs seems trite. The biggest problem isn't carrying the potluck food or making part of the journey a walk, it's the poor experience of taking the Boston subway, and spending about $8 dollars each each way for a trip that takes twice or thrice as long as a traffic free drive. We will rather drive and likely pay about 40 miles * $.50 / mile (where really only the $.10 mile gas price is obvious) for a total of $20 instead of $8 * 6 for three people, totaling $48 or $80 if you include the two other people now riding with us instead of taking trains. Should I be concerned that we're traveling as a 5 person carpool instead of using transit? In terms of pure CO2, probably not, but in terms of the transportation economic model I'm very concerned.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Transit needs group discounts just as you get by carpooling. Using commuter trains for regional transit should allow discounts when combining modes--here subway with train. But the system expects commuters, and thus only rewards those that buy a monthly pass and use subway and train twenty times a month. Why don't we start comparing car trips to multi-modal transit trips between the same points and ensuring that the transit is less than the car? Create a system that pulls tolls from cars and funds transit so we can manipulate the costs to favor the transit. Then see what happens with a level playing field.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Next time you drive somewhere, or take transit, calculate how much more expensive transit is than the cost per mile in gas (or use the true cost per mile if you are more inclined to think that way, which most people aren't.) If the one-way transit trip is $2 more than the one-way auto trip, ask if it would be better to pay a $2 auto toll to even it out or reduce the transit cost by $2 and funded by a progressive tax, like income tax, or a pollution tax--namely a carbon tax. I would love to start with a carbon tax at the gas pump that would make the auto trip $1 dollar more expensive and fund the transit to make it $1 dollar less expensive. From there we could keep increasing the tax until the transit was clearly less than the fuel costs of driving. You can call this tax regressive and unfair to the poor, but making the poor take transit isn't unfair if you fund your transit adequately. We have to start reducing car use somehow, and the best shot will always be going after people's wallets. I wish none of my friends could afford to drive, and that they preferred a transit system well-funded by the tax dollars of wealthy drivers, who increasingly found driving a luxury tax they wished to avoid.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-2646644522496881292?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/04/from-advocate-to-nag.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-7738542885645452638</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2010 03:27:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-03-31T20:27:55.495-07:00</atom:updated><title>Spring Break Breaks Momentum</title><description>I entered today with many distractions from spring break, which is a lousy thing to put in the middle of a semester. Besides that inertia, I have struggled to figure out what I think of participatory planning. My field project team is investigating it in a haphazard way, and I honestly don't know how I feel about the appropriate level of public involvement in the planning process. On the one hand, I want it to be maximal because there are a lot of good ideas and priceless knowledge out there. Unfortunately we are just learning how to effectively garner that data, and the software we are trying to use to do so is woefully inaccurate. Most of my ambition and work right now centers on advocating project with great software. As I proceed with various projects, I will document the experience here. For now I need to see who is in that business and find myself an internship.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-7738542885645452638?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/03/spring-break-breaks-momentum.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item><item><guid isPermaLink='false'>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-4858981700716628754.post-744015213255603643</guid><pubDate>Sat, 20 Mar 2010 00:57:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2010-03-22T10:36:54.791-07:00</atom:updated><title>Oh, the beautiful tramway</title><description>&lt;a href="http://streetcar.org/store/calendar/2010/images/calendar10-large.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://streetcar.org/store/calendar/2010/images/calendar10-large.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Confession, I've only ridden a couple tramways, or streetcars, or trolleys (a=b=c) in my life. The lovely historic F line in San Francisco along the Embarcadero and a couple of others which escape easy memory. I've ridden on plenty of street based light-rail service in San Francisco and Boston, which is pretty much the same as a tramway but for having vehicles designed for higher speeds along dedicated right-of-way. Inexperience aside, I never fail to advocate for them as the preferred alternative to any kind of bus service, whether local bus, bus rapid transit (BRT), or electric bus. The main reason for tramways is they convey a sense of permanence with their fixed rail, which can be placed straight down across a cobblestone public plaza, down a paved street, or on its own ballast alongside a road or completely removed from it. Even if you paint a special lane for BRT on the street with nice stations for boarding and alighting, you can't achieve the sense of security associated with parallel iron tracks. It can be hard at times to explain why the aesthetic, functional, and economic advantages of a tramway always make it a better option that BRT, because the initial cost of BRT is a bit lower. But I think even the South American cities like Curitiba, Brazil and Bogotá, Columbia, who have the most well known BRT systems, would have done better to have put in tramway service (or light rail.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://a1.vox.com/6a00c225286a34f21900d09e456a79be2b-500pi" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="http://a1.vox.com/6a00c225286a34f21900d09e456a79be2b-500pi" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;I am studying the French tramway renaissance that began in the 1980s after the passage of useful laws concerning urban transport, starting with the report &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.euromedina.org/bibliotheque_fichiers/Doc_TramCertu1.pdf"&gt;Planification urbaine et tramway en France,: le leçons de l'experience du tramway français moderne&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; (Urban planning and the tramway in France: The lessons of the experience of the modern French tramway.)&amp;nbsp; The first was the establishment of a public transit fund (&lt;i&gt;le Versement transport&lt;/i&gt;) in the early '70s that funded metro projects in the bigger cities, followed by a law on the direction of inner-city public transit in 1982&amp;nbsp; (&lt;i&gt;La Loi d’orientation des transports intérieurs (LOTI)&lt;/i&gt;), and in the '90s Plans of Urban Travel (&lt;i&gt;Les Plans de déplacements urbains (PDU)&lt;/i&gt;) were made obligatory in cities with more than 100,000 people for environmental reasons. The politics behind this led to the construction of several tramways. Several other transit and environmental laws continue to push tramway development, despite the French government pushing more of the funding obligations on the cities. In my constant attempt to better articulate the advantages of a tramway over a bus, I came upon these paragraphs of the report:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;Le tramway est d’abord un outil de transport. Il constitue, dans la gamme des systèmes de transport public, la réponse adaptée à une certaine demande : de capacité, de vitesse commerciale, de confort… Il correspond aux grandes orientations de la politique de mobilité durable prônée par la Loi sur l’air. Avec sa plateforme dédiée, sa priorité aux carrefours, il peut s’imposer de manière plus crédible face à la voiture individuelle et lui reprendre une partie de l’espace public qu’elle s’était accaparé dans les villes. &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The tramway is first a transit tool. It constitutes, in the range of systems of public transit, the response adapted to a certain demand: for capacity, commercial speed, and comfort... It corresponds to the major directions of the politics of sustainable mobility advocated by the "Law on air [quality]". With its dedicated platform, its priority in intersections, it can impose a more credible method to the individual car and retake from it a part of the public space that the car has monopolized in the cities.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;i&gt;Le tramway permet donc ce que ne permettait pas le bus. Mais le tramway n’est pas un métro pour autant : il ne transporte pas des foules énormes dans des tunnels noirs. Il est ouvert sur la ville et visible depuis la ville. Des architectes, des designers, des paysagistes vont mettre à profit cette visibilité pour donner un peu de réalité au concept abstrait de développement durable, dont les retombées positives ne peuvent se voir qu’à très long terme. Le tramway donne une impression d’amélioration environnementale immédiate : silence et absence de pollution de l’air, plantations d’arbres, plateforme végétalisée… Il rend la ville durable maintenant.&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;The tramway thus permits what is not permitted by the bus.&amp;nbsp; But for all that, the tramway is not a metro: it does not transport enormous crowds in dark tunnels. It is open onto the city and visible from the city. Architects, designers, and landscape architects are going to take advantage of this visibility to give a bit of reality to the abstract concept of sustainable development, whose positive benefits can only be shown in the long term. The tramway gives an impression of immediate environmental improvement: The silence and absence of pollution of the air, plantation of trees, landscaped platforms...It makes the city sustainable now.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In other words, what the tramway accomplishes is unique and unobtainable, despite the best of intentions, with BRT. Unfortunately, BRT also permits the cutting of corners--maintaining reliance on diesel fuel or natural gas instead of electricity (or possibly hydrogen), giving only partial right-of-way (see the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Silver_Line_%28MBTA%29"&gt;Boston Silver Line&lt;/a&gt; (a.k.a. the Silver Lie)), and not using prepay stations (though this isn't always done with streetcars either.) Most anyone who has experienced the most modern of buses and rail-based vehicles also knows that a bus cannot match the smooth comfort of rails.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The last thing I'll say about BRT is a bit unfair, but needs to be said. Buses replaced streetcars. People generally liked streetcars (I've read) and generally don't like buses (I know.) If you want to put people on public transit and take away their desire to drive (I do,) then you can't simply spruce up the bus with BRT and expect a mindset change. No, you need to bring back a modern version of the technology, the level-of-service, and the travel experience that proudly explains "I am first-class transit! I am not a bus! Though I serve those that are transit dependent with low fares, I equally serve those who used to drive but now prefer me as their chosen lifestyle."&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I am beginning an advocacy campaign for the restoration of many of the streetcar lines in my current home in Somerville, MA, in Cambridge, Boston, and its suburbs. The biggest challenge is to give them the right-of-way that they need. To do so I must find solutions that remove lanes of traffic and/or parking in a sane, logical way, that improves the quality of life for the majority.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In a future post, I want to break down the costs and benefits of streetcars versus BRT. I have at least one book that explores different transit modes thoroughly, so I'll convey its findings and whatever other information I come across.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/4858981700716628754-744015213255603643?l=degagelavoie.blogspot.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><link>http://degagelavoie.blogspot.com/2010/03/oh-beautiful-tramway.html</link><author>andy@likuski.org (Andy)</author><thr:total>0</thr:total></item></channel></rss>
